This one always just takes my breath away because it's so beautiful and it's so colorful.
But the messaging, you know, the worlding messages, I almost feel like a deep, deep urgency just following how this works. So there's and it's so it's actually really complex. So.
Take us take us through.
Well, I want to hear you talking about it.
You're looking at it was precise.
There we.
The message is clear that's a slogan that was popularized by was referred to as the anti globalization movement. It really means anti corporate globalization.
The imagery on one side is, you know, shows, you know, power plants, strip mining pipelines, police, confronting protesters, devastated, Tarsans landscapes and so forth. And the person is
pushing through to a future of renewable energy community agriculture and abundance really right. And it's based on a 19th century woodcut that mimicking medieval art.
Right.
And the original shows somebody looking through to the grinding gears of the universe, right when they had the very mechanistic renaissance view of the way the universe worked. It works like a machine.
He's really into machines, everything's a machine, right. You can peer past the facade and you can see the gears of the of the universe turning right. And obviously this is the one thing that hasn't common besides a direct appropriation of the design is that it's moving. It's looking from one world into another.
In this case, from the present into a future, right.
I mean, there's things I love about it. I love the fact that this, you know, from the razor wire and the battery and the cameras.
And then they become like the helicopter, this militarization, right, and securitization of everything becomes this beautiful space over here of bees and vines.
And, you know, this, this image to like I almost can, to me, it's like I just feel this exhaustion, this person carrying the reclaim the common sign and they're like, I can see it. It's there.
You know, I can see it. And then this, this beauty that feels, you know, it does feel like it's being pushed. It's, it's out. But, but there is still a sky overlap, which gives me hope to.
And also you also see this whole row of police with shields, we've been able to be shields and where they can find the confirming resistance.
You know, that resistance is here in the present. That's where that future ultimately will grow from. And you also see a line of people protecting a forest.
And this, I think, is a piece that captures your work too in the sense that I think.
I just, I think there are, there are so many folks we're going to talk with and have been talking with who are who are doing such amazing work. I think there's, it's hard to find someone who's done as much work as you have across so many fronts and so many issues.
And in fact, almost can condense them into a space like this image, which, you know, crosses over into food into energy into sustainability into.
The carceral into labor and I mean, it's all there. Great. It's all there and away.
I think to me, the idea that another world is possible is a lot more complex than it seems on the face of it. It's the same as with police abolition.
That it's something that people can easily relate to as kind of a cathartic fantasy that they can hold on to while they slug through a universe of in the suppression.
Right.
So part of the challenge to me is to make that actually feel practical.
You know, to make a continuation of the police system as we know it seem naive.
An abolition seeming the only pragmatic future, which it is right.
The thing with this is like simply putting on a slapping a smiley face on grim realities is not the same as helping people understand that things don't have to be the way they are.
They weren't always they got that way through history, through actions, through intention, which means that they can also go another way through all those same forces.
Right. Which in part means to me that you know, it's sort of a doctor healed, I self kind of principle that for me to be able to make that credible.
I have to believe it. I have to feel that I have to understand it, which means that I have to study reality.
It means I have to understand something about how trauma holds us back about how history replicates itself about all of these things about why we reenact.
Oppressive behaviors on each other.
Because if we don't go straight towards them walk toward them and look them in the face, then you know, as they say we're doomed to repeat them.
But when we can do that, we can see that oh, none of this is inevitable.
One of the quotes you said, Ray, is that we have to ask what harm was so huge.
This is the moment.
And it's so huge that it damaged our inherent ability to be hopeful.
And that speaks to I think what worlding work does and the healing component of it is it does it's pragmatic.
You're absolutely right. Like that image does work. Like I know what I want when I see that.
Yeah, and part of that idea about trauma damaging our inherent capacities is connected to looking at the natural world right and looking at the animals of the forest through the ocean or the trees right that as they head out and.
You know engage in their daily or nightly life. They're looking for food. They're looking for mates. They're looking for nesting places. They're looking for something that's all hope.
Hope is what drives every one of these organisms in one way or another right.
So that when we find ourselves healing, you know, being hopeless is like that is a serious malfunction of our emotional immune systems right.
And it's not I like to describe it as not being an emotion despair is not an emotion.
Because emotions give us useful information.
You know fear and joy and grief and all of these things.
But despair gives us a message that it's not worth.
It's not worth collecting information.
Information is what we use to make choices and disparities. There are no choices to be made. It's not worth it. Just don't even bother getting out of bed. Don't look.
Right. So that is a serious form of damage right that in itself is what we need to repair in order that all of this information can come flowing in that can provide us guidance can.
You know can help us see opportunity and possibility when we sort of riff off of what I said a moment ago about on creatures being drawn or driven by hope.
That essentially abolition means removing the obstacles to that.
Right. So that you can have imagery that's about how we can relate to each other in humane and regenerative and sustainable and accountable ways.
And that's abolition in the sense that in order to achieve that there are some shackles that got to be broken.
There are some obstacles that need to be removed both internally and externally that they need to be abolished right.
You know it can also be abolitionist to look at specifically highlight what those chains are.
What are the issues. What are the institutions. What are the practices. What is the history that we have come. What's the trauma that we need to heal from.
But it doesn't have to be that quite that specific.
And one of the things that I think makes the use of the abolitionist language appropriate in this moment.
And the question is, what are the reasons why we're talking about the unfinished business of emancipation.
These are part and parcel of the effort especially to prevent the promise of emancipation from actually interfering with the gathering of profit.
So I have, I don't, I'm not resolved about this, but I have questions about where their abolition was the appropriate language to have been using in the 19th century.
Right. And I wasn't there in the tactical choices and strategic choices that people make.
It's hard to second guess them from from the distance because there's so much we don't really know about sort of the the body language of the moment.
And one of the limitations of abolition is that the word itself is just about getting rid of something.
It's not about liberation per se.
And Frederick Douglass warned against the, you know, against complacency. I mean, he was very clear that abolition might not leave the liberation.
But the language of abolition on the one level allowed for a broader united front.
But on the other hand, it's limiting because it means that once those chains are broken, kind of like our work is done.
And a lot of the people who were active in that moment didn't know what to do afterwards.
It's like even Frederick Douglass at times was in later decades into the language of well, you know, you all got to pull yourself up a bootstraps.
And so, you know, I think it's a lot of the things that I think we need to do more.
There are no further obstacles other than ourselves that was never true.
Right. So anyway, it's just the complexity of history.
I think given all of that history, it makes a lot of sense to use that.
But I think we need to imbue it. And I'm glad to see that so many people are with a sense of moving toward a future that abolition is not just a getting rid of it's what gets to grow in its place.